Guide to the Gorham Munson Papers on the American Social Credit Movement and New Democracy, 1899 - 1969, bulk 1932 - 1945
Gorham Munson Papers on the American Social Credit Movement and New Democracy, 1899 - 1969, bulk 1932 - 1945
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Munson, Gorham.
1000-18
38.5
49
Social Credit has been an economic theory, a social philosophy, an ideology, and a political party in England, Canada, Australia, New Zealand, and the United States since it was first advanced in 1920 by Major C. H. Douglas. He believed finance capitalism deprived individuals of sufficient purchasing power to buy otherwise available products. To overcome this Douglas proposed offering to every citizen dividend payments based on the community's real wealth. As monetary reform and as social theory Social Credit attracted intellectual support in England and the United States especially during the 1930s. Gorham Munson (Wesleyan class of 1917) was the most eloquent and durable Social Credit leader in the United States. In 1932, he became American correspondent for The New English Weekly, defended Social Credit in The Nation and helped form a key Social Credit organization, the New Economics Group of New York. In 1933 he initiated a vital Social Credit journal of the arts and public affairs, New Democracy, and was its chief editor during its three-year life.
The papers of Gorham Munson (1896-1969) deal almost wholly with his support of Social Credit and are confined to the years 1932 to 1945. There is almost no information about his career as a literary critic, book editor, and teacher of writing. The material includes articles, books, correspondence, pamphlets, and scrapbooks. The collection grew out of Munson's interconnected roles as organizer, publicist, fund-raiser, editor, promoter, lobbyist, propagandist, theorist, leader, and diplomat for a succession of Social Credit organizations from 1932 to 1945. Published materials provide the best documentation of the development of the theory of Social Credit in England, Canada, the United States, Australia, and New Zealand. Major correspondents include Ezra Pound, his father Homer Pound, James Laughlin IV, William Carlos Williams, Major C. H. Douglas, John Hargrave, Philip Mairet, Stanley Mott, Lilly Bierne, Herbert Bruce Brougham, Allan R. Brown, Howard L. Buck, A. M. Edwards, Paul Hampden, Laurence Morris, W. A. Nyland, A. H. Spencer, Elliott Taylor, and Mrs. E. Sohier Welch. Congressional correspondents include Charles G. Binderup, Fred L. Crawford, T. Alan Goldsborough and Jerry F. Voorhis. There are also files on the New English Weekly and The Beacon of Winnipeg, which incorporated New Democracy in 1937-1939.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Wesleyan University acquired the Munson Social Credit papers from Gorham Munson, class of 1917, through one purchase, 1966, and a series of gifts, 1966 to 1975. Purchase of 144 typewritten and holograph letters from Ezra Pound to Munson and Pound's pamphlet Alfred Venison's Poems was made from the Caroline Clark Barney Fund for the purchase of poetry. The initial gift of 52 additional letters was judged important by an appraiser for the university as illustrating the way in which during the Great Depression leading writers and artists were attracted by an unorthodox and rather abstruse economic theory. Munson gave Wesleyan a second selection of papers in 1966, three in 1968, and three more in 1969 just before his death. Since then, his widow, Elizabeth Delza Munson has, according to his express wishes, made additional gifts.
Bibliography of Books by Gorham Munson
Waldo Frank: A Study. New York: Boni and Liveright, 1923. 95 pp. Reprinted 1975, Folcroft Library Edition, Folcroft, Pennsylvania.
Robert Frost: A Study in Sensibility and Good Sense. New York: George H. Doran Co., 1927. 135 pp. Reprinted 1970, Haskell House Pubs. Ltd., New York; 1970, Kennikat Press, Port Washington, New York
Destinations: A Canvass of American Literature Since 1900. New York: J. H. Sears & Col, Inc., 1928. 218 pp. Reprinted 1970, AMS Press, New York; 1971, Scholarly Press, St. Clair Shores, Michigan.
Style and Form in American Prose. Garden City, New York: Doubleday, Doran & Co., Inc., 1929. 313 pp. Reprinted 1969, Kennikat Press.
The Dilemma of the Liberated: An Interpretation of Twentieth Century Humanism. New York: Coward-McCann, Inc., 1930. 304 pp. Reprinted 1967, Kennikat Press.
Twelve Decisive Battles of the Mind: The Story of Propaganda During the Christian Era, with Abridged Versions of Texts That Have Shaped History. New York: Greystone Press, 1942. 280 pp. Reprinted 1968, Books for Libraries Press, Freeport, New York.
Aladdin's Lamp: The Wealth of the American People. New York: Creative Age Press, 1945. 420 pp.
The Written Word: How to Write Readable Prose. New York: Creative Age Press, 1949. 285 pp. Reprinted 1962, Collier Books, New York.
The Writer's Workshop Companion. New York: Farrar, Straus and Young, 1951. 310 pp. Reprinted 1969, Greenwood Press, Westport, Connecticut.
Best Advice on How to Write: An Anthology. Edited by Gorham Munson. New York: Hermitage House, 1952. 290 pp.
Penobscot: Down East Paradise. Philadelphia: Lippincott, 1959. 299 pp. Reprinted 1975, Down East Enterprises, Camden, Maine.
Robert Frost: Making Poems for America. Chicago: Encyclopedia Britannica Press, 1962. 190 pp.
The Awakening Twenties: a Memoir-History of a Literary Period. Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 1985.
Historical Note
Social Credit has been an economic theory, a social philosophy, an ideology, and a political party in England, Canada, Australia, New Zealand, and the United States since it was first advanced in 1920 by Major C. H. Douglas. He believed finance capitalism deprived individuals of sufficient purchasing power to buy otherwise available products. To overcome this Douglas proposed offering to every citizen dividend payments based on the community's real wealth. As monetary reform and as social theory Social Credit attracted intellectual support in England and the United States especially during the 1930s. Only in Canada, however, did Social Credit become an important movement with a political base and there only in the provinces of Alberta, British Columbia, and Quebec.
In the United Kingdom:
In The Long Week End [The Long Week End: A Social History of Great Britain, 1918-1939 (New York: Macmillan, 1941), pp. 296-297], Robert Graves and Alan Hodge pointed out that the British proletariat between the wars was attracted by more plausible remedies than a revolution. One of the remedies to economic ills was Social Credit. Graves and Hodge continue:
Major C. H. Douglas, a retired Royal Engineer, had been propounding his theory of Social Credit in a series of books and pamphlets for over ten years. In the thirties a Social Credit party was formed; its members adopted the new political habit of wearing coloured shirts as uniforms, and chose green. The Daily Mail honoured the party with a mention in its Year Book for 1935. Serious economists criticized it in the serious weeklies, and T. S. Eliot, who had banking and commercial experience as well as literary eminence, welcomed it as a promising solution of the world's troubles. By 1935 the movement had spread to the Dominions. In Alberta, Canada, a Social Credit party was elected to the provincial legislature, pledged to distribute dollar bills periodically to the electorate. But like all economic plans, however sound in general theory, it could not be applied in a single isolated context, and many banking and business interests in Alberta took flight to other provinces of the Dominion; so that the Social Credit party, which was not even unanimous on practical policy, was starved into surrender.
The Social Credit plan was to distribute national dividends to everyone through the central banks. The basis of the value of these dividends was supposed to be the capital equipment and the energy possessed by the community. The present financial system, Major Douglas held, did not reflect the real credit of the community. To prove this, he developed a theory meant to show that some of the country's income was continuously lost by the interest charges of the banking system. Dividends for All would remedy this by bringing a country's purchasing power up to the level of its productive power. Social Credit took for granted that modern science enabled productive power to be increased limitlessly, even to the point of luxury for all. From this followed the first step in its argument: that only a lack of purchase power prevented the masses from enjoying the natural increase.
Serious people were glad to find a theory which seemed to provide a non-political solution for the world's troubles, the more so because the banks seemed the obvious scapegoats for the Depression. Not many people knew what was the function of banks, and the rest could easily be induced to look on them as concerns that exploited the public for the benefit of their directors. Major Douglas himself, however, pointed out that he regarded bankers not as dishonestly anti-social, but as victims of their own system. He wrote in 1934 of the necessity for exalting the individual over the group. I mean by that the exact opposite of what is commonly called Socialism. The direct road to the emancipation of the individual from the domination of the group is, in my opinion, the substitution, to an increasing extent, of the dividend in place of the wage and salary. Such words were more than welcome to people who feared that their lives would be exactly regulated by Socialist or Totalitarian economics; but neither the orthodox nor the Socialist economists had any difficulty in pointing out the flaws in his argument. The Social Credit theory was never adopted by any influential political group in Great Britain. It merely provided another controversial topic.
Although Social Credit attracted only a small following in Britain, its roots must be remembered to have been English. For this reason, brief sketches of the key men are included in these outlines, which will set the stage for a better understanding of the migration of Social Credit to Canada and to the United States.
CLIFFORD HUGH DOUGLAS, 1879-1952. An engineer with experience in India, Douglas attained the rank of major in the Royal Aircraft Establishment during World War I, retiring in 1918. His ideas on Social Credit were first advanced in articles in The English Review and The New Age. His earliest books were Economic Democracy in 1920 and Social Credit in 1924. Little is known either of his personal life or his professional career. Having had no training in economics, Douglas looked upon Social Credit as a total solution to the world's problems and, consequently, rejected such rival approaches as Guild Socialism, Fabianism, Socialism, or Bolshevism. He may be said to have opposed capitalism on economic grounds and Socialism on political grounds. Social Credit as an idea never escaped its founder's fear of political leadership which he coupled with a messianic approach and inept propaganda. Thus Douglas agreed to advise the Social Credit government in Alberta in 1935, but disagreements led quickly to his resignation. He corresponded with Munson and other Social Credit advocates in the United States and, in 1934, visited New York and Washington. That his style was enigmatic is shown by his belief in individual freedom while insisting, whenever invited to be active in an organization to promote Social Credit, on total power for himself. Thus in 1933, when asked to join the National Credit Association, Douglas demanded absolute authority, a Douglas veto over any proposed members of the conference, and a preliminary agenda committee appointed by Douglas personally. [John L. Finlay, The English Origins of Social Credit (Montreal and London: McGill-Queen's University Press, 1972), p. 133.] This flaw coupled with his anti-Semitism reduced his influence after 1935.
Major Douglas viewed payments made by a productive organization as falling into two groups. He labeled payments made to individuals Group A, those to other organizations Group B. This was explained, as can be seen below, but the A Plus B Theorem became a kind of shorthand for adherents of Social Credit, for Douglas advanced it as an indication and test of Social Credit genuineness. This is his explanation:
Group A--All payments made to individuals (wages, salaries and dividends). Group B--All payments made to other organizations (raw materials, bank charges, and other external costs). Now the rate of flow of purchasing power to individuals is represented by A, but since all payments go into prices the rate of flow of prices cannot be less than A + B. The product of any factory may be considered as something which the public ought to be able to buy, although in many cases it is an intermediate product of no use to individuals, but only to a subsequent manufacture; but since A will not purchase A + B, a proportion of the product at least equivalent to B must be distributed by some form of purchasing power which is not comprised in the descriptions grouped under A. It will be necessary at a a later stage to show that this additional purchasing power is provided by loan credits (bank overdrafts) or export credit. [Clifford Hugh Douglas, Credit-Power and Democracy (London: Cecil Palmer, 1920), p. 22; rev. ed. (London: Stanley Nott, 1934), pp. 19-20.]
ALFRED RICHARD ORAGE, 1873-1934. As editor of the influential New Age from 1907-1922, Orage gave the ideas of Social Credit their first continuous exposition. Orage opened its pages to Major Douglas beginning in 1918. He was important in both England and the United States as a spokesman and interpreter of Social Credit thereafter. After 1922, Orage was drawn to Georgi Gurdjieff's psychological method for the harmonious development of man. In 1932 he founded the New English Weekly, as a Social Credit organ. [See Herbert B. Grimsditch, A. R. Orage, Dictionary of National Biography, 1931-1940, Oxford University Press, 1949, p. 659. For excerpts from Orage's writings, see Wallace Martin, ed., Orage as Critic (London: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1974.)]
H. E. B. LUDHAM. A Coventry printer prominent in a rightwing split in the Social Credit movement that began at the Swanwick conference in 1925. This group, which also included Frederick Soddy, a Nobel laureate in chemistry, and Arthur Kitson, called itself the Economic Freedom League. Ludham edited the League's journal, the Age of Plenty. Favoring centralization and political action, Ludham stood for election in the 1938 Coventry municipal election and lost. In the late 1920s and in the 1930s, Ludham became associated with John Strachey and Sir Oswald Mosley of the British Union of Fascists. (See Finlay, English Origins, pp. 126-29, 206, 211.)
JOHN HARGRAVE, 1894-1982. A man of great personal force, unorthodox in the fullest sense, greatly interested in monetary reform, Hargrave did not come to an awareness of Social Credit until 1927. Earlier he was interested in scouting and led such off-beat organizations as the White Fox, Wa-Whaw-Goosh and the Kibbo Kift. Courted by social crediters running the New Age as well as by the rival Economic Freedom League in its columns in the Age of Plenty, Hargrave tended toward the former but favored mass action through a Third Line between Fascism and Communism. He quickly became the most prominent social credit man in England, apart from Douglas, leading a movement with a succession of different titles: the Economic Party, 1929-1930; the Crusader Legion in Coventry, 1930-1933; an inner elite known as the Iron Guard and then as the Green Shirts; the Green Shirt Movement for Social Credit, 1933-1935; and finally, the Social Credit Party of Great Britain. Traditionally antiparliamentary, the Social Credit Party ran a candidate for the House of Commons in South Leeds but gained only 11 per cent of the vote. Hargrave feuded with Douglas, and the Green Shirts, in uniform, broke up a Social Credit reception for one of Douglas's Hargrave had become an hysterical mystic, and the militant Green Shirts was largely ended by the Public Order Act outlawing the use of uniforms for political purposes. For some years, Hargrave edited This Week's Message from Hargrave. He rejected both Fascism and Communism and believed that only a monarch could stand up to the conspiracy of the money trust and, on this ground, took the side of Edward VIII in the abdication crisis of 1937. (See Finlay, English Origins, chapter 7.)
In Canada
The best concise summary of the kindling of Social Credit in Canada is to be found in The Oxford Companion to Canadian History and Literature, by Norah Story (Toronto, London, New York: Oxford University Press, 1967, p. 772), quoted here in full:
Social Credit Party. A popular movement, led by William Aberhart, that won the Alberta provincial election in 1935, it was disciplined into a political party that has remained in power in Alberta, has invaded the federal field, and has spread to other provinces. It came into power in British Columbia in 1952.
The intricate monetary scheme and social philosophy known as social credit was enunciated in England by Maj. Clifford Douglas. At the instigation of William Irvine, Douglas was brought to Canada in 1923 where he was invited to explain his views to the House of Commons' Select Committee on Banking and Commerce. He made a poor impression on all but the UFA (United Farmers of Alberta) members, who distributed social credit in their province. The theory of social credit was brought to the attention of William Aberhart, a high-school principal in Calgary whose Sunday radio broadcasts as head of the fundamentalist Prophetic Bible Institute had a large and enthusiastic following. In 1932 Aberhart began to introduce his own vague theories of social credit into these broadcasts, recommending a redistribution of purchasing power and later, as head of the Social Credit Party, promising a social dividend of $25 a month to every citizen. Followers of Douglas attacked his interpretation, and the resulting public debate and paper warfare stimulated public interest. In 1934 Douglas was brought to Alberta as 'reconstruction adviser' to the UFA government. This move created an outpouring of sentiment on behalf of Aberhart. Social Credit candidates were selected in the constituencies, but Aberhart personally chose which of these should stand. They swept the province in the election of 1935 and Aberhart became the premier.
Acts passed in Alberta in 1937 to implement social credit monetary theories were disallowed by the federal government or declared unconstitutional. The Social Credit Bill of Rights, passed under Aberhart's successor, E. C. Manning, was appealed to the privy council where it too was declared unconstitutional. These decisions have given impetus to campaigning for seats in parliament in the hope that, with a majority, the constitution could be amended. The party gained 17 federal seats in 1935. Thereafter membership fluctuated until 1958 when no member was elected, but 30 seats were won in 1962 and 24 in 1963 when the representation was weakened by the members from Quebec who organized as a separate group.
ABERHART SOCIAL CREDIT DOCTRINE. The conditions of life in Alberta during the Great Depression made social credit attractive: they also modified the ideas of Douglas. The class makeup of Alberta and the debtor position there had produced a tradition of looking for monetary cures to economic troubles. Additionally there was a strong predilection for prophetic religion so that a leader of Aberhart's charismatic traits easily gained a large following. These three circumstances made Alberta, as a community, far more receptive than was England to a monetary reform doctrine with spiritual overtones. They made it possible for social credit to become a mass movement, and in so doing ensured the vulgarization of the social and economic doctrine of Major Douglas. [C. B. Macpherson, Democracy in Alberta: The Theory and Practice of a Quasi-Party System. (Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1953), p. 148.] Aberhart reduced the Douglas doctrine to the simple points of A plus B, the unearned increment, the basic dividend, and the just price.
ALBERTA SOCIAL CREDIT PROGRAM, 1935-1943. As premier of the first social credit government in the world for eight years, William Aberhart's program has been characterized as politically radical but economically conservative. He and his constituents wished to divorce themselves from the central government in Ottawa without making profound changes in Alberta. Three key measures were enacted in 1937: (1) the Credit of Alberta Regulation Act, (2) the Bank Employees Civil Rights Act, and (3) the Judicature Act Amendment Act. A stunning thing then happened. Under its federal system, the central government in Ottawa disallowed these provincial statutes and this was upheld in rulings of the Canadian Supreme Court and the British Privy Council. There is much more to the story, but in 1938 the essence of the Social Credit program was dead. It meant that Aberhart's program of social credit eventually failed even in name. [J. R. Mallory, Social Credit and the Federal Power in Canada. (Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1954), pp. 57-90.]
SOCIAL CREDIT IN CANADA, 1943-1976. With a hold on Alberta established, Social Credit developed branches in other provinces, first in Saskatchewan and then in British Columbia where it came to power in 1952. [See Martin Robin, The Social Basis of Party Politics in British Columbia, in H. G. Thorburn, ed., Party Politics in Canada, 2nd ed. (Scarborough, Ont.: Prentice-Hall of Canada, Ltd., 1967), pp. 201-211.] At the provincial level in recent years, the Social Credit Party has shown significant strength in Alberta, British Columbia and Quebec. In federal elections its chief strength has been in Quebec where 20 per cent of the total vote has been won, while elsewhere Social Credit has fallen to less than 5 per cent. [For a close examination of the appeal and success of Social Credit in the 1962 elections in Quebec Province, see Maurice Pinard, The Rise of a Third Party: A Study in Crisis Politics (Englewood Cliffs, New Jersey: Prentice-Hall, Inc., 1971). For a sociological and political study, see Michael Stein, The Dynamics of Right-Wing Protest: A Political Analysis of Social Credit in Quebec (Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 1973).]
In the United States
The Social Credit ideas of Major C. H. Douglas were adopted in the United States by a small group of intellectuals who advanced this monetary reform from 1932 to 1945 through a succession of small organizations and publications. Electoral support was never sought as in Canada. The early influences were from Ezra Pound, the self-exiled poet and A. R. Orage, the English editor who lived in the United States in the twenties. Pound first wrote about the wisdom of Major Douglas in The Little Review in April 1920. He became a zealous advocate of Social Credit and influenced such figures as William Carlos Williams and, later, James Laughlin IV. Orage's influence is difficult to calculate, but his impact on artists and writers in New York was profound, as they have attested. He cultivated an American readership for his Social Credit journal, The New English Weekly, founded in 1932. More than any other single element, this publication marked the beginning of the organized study of Social Credit in the United States.